<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Project on The Data Sandbox</title>
    <link>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/categories/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Project on The Data Sandbox</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://datasandbox.netlify.app/categories/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Underrated CRAN Packages</title>
      <link>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-03-31-underrated-cran-packages/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-03-31-underrated-cran-packages/</guid>
      <description>I sit here looking for inspiration, nothing interesting to write about. Perhaps there are some popular R packages on CRAN that I don’t know about? You can explore the data on downloads from CRAN with the cranlogs package.
Top CRAN downloadsWith the following code we can get the most popular packages from CRAN. The CRAN directory doesn’t represent all R packages but a good amount of them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bike shares in Toronto</title>
      <link>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-02-27-bike-shares-in-toronto/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-02-27-bike-shares-in-toronto/</guid>
      <description>Photo by Maarten van den Heuvel on Unsplash
This article is based on a project written on 01/14/2021
Bike Rental Shiny AppThis application use the data collected from the Toronto Open Data to generate a histogram of the usage of rental bikes in Toronto during the month of June in 2020.
install.packages(&amp;quot;opendatatoronto&amp;quot;, repos = &amp;quot;http://cran.us.r-project.org&amp;quot;,dependencies = TRUE)library(opendatatoronto)library(tidyverse)library(lubridate)library(shiny)UIThere are two user inputs on the UI side:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Speed cameras in Toronto</title>
      <link>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-02-16-/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-02-16-/</guid>
      <description>Photo by Sepideh Golchin Rad on Unsplash
This project was originally written on 02/01/2021 as part of the Data Productscourse for the Data Science Specialization from Johns Hopkins University on Coursera
ObjectiveThis report plots the speed cameras in the Greater Toronto Area from the data providedby Open Toronto which can be found here.
InializationThe following code is used to initialize the required libraries.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Job posting analysis</title>
      <link>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-01-30-job-posting-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-01-30-job-posting-analysis/</guid>
      <description>Recently, there was a post on medium about the use of Natural Language Processing (NLP)to study a job posting for keywords. I found that this article was very similar toR shiny App that I created a while ago. 1
IntroductionTechnology has changed the job application process, making it easier and quicker toapply to jobs. As a result, the average job posting will receive around 250 resumes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fitness Tracker Modeling: ML</title>
      <link>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-01-29-fitness-tracker-modeling-ml/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-01-29-fitness-tracker-modeling-ml/</guid>
      <description>The original paper was written on 12/18/2020
Executive SummaryThis report analyzes collected data on different users preforming barbell liftsperformed at different levels of quality. A machine learning algorithm was usedto create a model to determine the user’s rating based on data collected from multipleaccelerometers. More information on the project can be found here.
AnalysisInitializationThe following code was used to initialize the required R libraries, as well as downloading the required data and store it into memory.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
