<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>General on The Data Sandbox</title>
    <link>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/categories/general/</link>
    <description>Recent content in General on The Data Sandbox</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://datasandbox.netlify.app/categories/general/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Level up your programming skills</title>
      <link>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-05-01-level-up-your-progamming-skills/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-05-01-level-up-your-progamming-skills/</guid>
      <description>How do you become a better programmer? Well, there is strong scientific evidence for the support of the principle of deliberate practice. Deliberate practice is a method of skill development first written by Anders Ericsson in the book “Peak: Secrets from the New Science of Expertise”. I would also recommend reading “Talent Is Overrated: What Really Separates World-Class Performers from Everybody Else” by Geoff Colvin.
Deliberate PracticeDeliberate Practice can be summarized to the following points:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R-Bloggers site</title>
      <link>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-04-11-r-bloggers-site/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-04-11-r-bloggers-site/</guid>
      <description>I would like to take the time to mention the r-bloggers site. It is a vast collection of Blogs on everything that has to do will the R language. I would very much like to contribute to their work with this blog.
Just to keep it interesting, I would like to recommend this specific post by The Jumping Rivers Blog about upcoming R conferences. I’ve attended a few digital R Conferences, hosted by R-Studio, and they are very rewarding experiences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New features in R</title>
      <link>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-02-23-new-features-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-02-23-new-features-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Photo by Clint Patterson on Unsplash
Recently I had updated my RStudio client and with it came a new update to R. This is an exploration of some of the most interesting changes from R 4.0 to R 4.1.
Native Pipe FunctionDue to the extreme popularity of the magrittr pipe (‘%&amp;gt;%’), R has developed its own native pipe (‘|&amp;gt;’).
library(tidyverse)data(&amp;quot;morley&amp;quot;)morley |&amp;gt;group_by(Expt) |&amp;gt;summarise(mean = mean(Speed, na.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
