<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Python on The Data Sandbox</title>
    <link>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/tags/python/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Python on The Data Sandbox</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://datasandbox.netlify.app/tags/python/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Simple Neural Networks in Python</title>
      <link>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-03-20-simple-neural-networks-in-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-03-20-simple-neural-networks-in-python/</guid>
      <description>Neural Networks (NN) have become incredibly popular due to their high level of accuracy. The creation of a NN can be complicated and have a high level of customization. I wanted to explore just the simplest NN that you could create. A framework as a workhorse for developing new NN.
The SciKitlearn provides the easiest solution with the Multi-Layer Perceptron series of functions. It doesn’t provide a bunch of the more advanced features of TensorFlow, like GPU support, but that is not what I’m looking for.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Python in R Markdown</title>
      <link>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-03-03-python-in-r-markdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-03-03-python-in-r-markdown/</guid>
      <description>Photo by David Clode on Unsplash
The main advantage of using the R Markdown format is the utility of running R code within the text. This is clearly more advantageous than just writing code in a Markdown file. RMarkdown is however limited to R code, unable to run Python scripts. The R library reticulate looks to add this capability.
Initial SetupThe initial setup requires the installation of the reticulate library, after installation you shouldn’t need to call it, but I do in the preceding code.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
