<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>GGPlot on The Data Sandbox</title>
    <link>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/tags/ggplot/</link>
    <description>Recent content in GGPlot on The Data Sandbox</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://datasandbox.netlify.app/tags/ggplot/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Making the Connection with Crosstalk</title>
      <link>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-03-18-making-the-connection-with-crosstalk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-03-18-making-the-connection-with-crosstalk/</guid>
      <description>I recently wrote a post about creating dashboards in R which was based on the Flexdashboard library. My largest criticism was the lack of communication between visualizations on the same dashboard. This was before I learned about the Crosstalk package which adds this feature to html widgets, such as the Flexdashboard, to at least a limited degree.
InitializationThe Crosstalk package is available on CRAN and is loaded along with other important packages for this demonstration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating Dashboards in R</title>
      <link>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-03-10-creating-dashboard-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-03-10-creating-dashboard-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Dashboards are a great way to demonstrate knowledge and engage decision makers. Their utility has made PowerBI andTableau household names. And while these solutions do support R and Python scripts and visualizations, the Flexdashboard package seeks to compete. The Flexdashboard packages does this all in R with the simplicity of writing a R Markdown file.
Initial SetupThe setup is simple, you just need to download and load the Flexdashboard package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fitness Tracker Modeling: ML</title>
      <link>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-01-29-fitness-tracker-modeling-ml/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://datasandbox.netlify.app/post/2022-01-29-fitness-tracker-modeling-ml/</guid>
      <description>The original paper was written on 12/18/2020
Executive SummaryThis report analyzes collected data on different users preforming barbell liftsperformed at different levels of quality. A machine learning algorithm was usedto create a model to determine the user’s rating based on data collected from multipleaccelerometers. More information on the project can be found here.
AnalysisInitializationThe following code was used to initialize the required R libraries, as well as downloading the required data and store it into memory.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
